# Chris Hancock (he/him) | Curriculum Vitae

PhD Candidate, Northern Arizona University

clh624@nau.edu | 617-932-9777 | Website | LinkedIn | Google Scholar | Orchid | GitHub

### **Research Interests**

I am a climate and data scientist. My current research combines information from paleoclimate proxies with climate model simulations to reconstruct the response of regional hydroclimate variability to global climate change in the geologic past. To do this, I develop and manage large multi-proxy datasets and utilize analytical techniques such as timeseries analysis, geospatial statistics, and data assimilation. These results provide insight into modern climate dynamics and the impacts of current climate change on the global hydrological cycle.

### Education

| Northern Arizona University — PhD Earth Science & Environmental Sustainability                | 2020 — 2024 |
|---|-------------|
| Dissertation: Reconstructing Holocene Hydroclimate through a Data Assimilation Approach       |             |
| Advisor: Dr. Nick McKay   |             |
| University of Denver — MA Geography   | 2018 — 2020 |
| Thesis: Spatial and Temporal Controls on Streamflow Variability in the San Juan Mountains, CO |             |
| Advisor: Dr. J. Michael Daniels   |             |
| George Washington University — BS Geological Sciences   | 2010 — 2014 |
| Minors in Geography and Geographical Information Science                                      |             |
| Advisor: Dr. Richard Tollo  |             |

### **Professional Experience**

| Research Assistant — Northern Arizona University                 | Aug. 2020 — Present   |
|--|-----------------------|
| PaleoDynamics Lab (Advisor: Dr. Nick McKay), Flagstaff, AZ       |                       |
| Raw Water Operations Intern — Denver Water                       | May 2019 — Aug. 2019  |
| Water Resources Strategy Section, Denver, CO                     |                       |
| Support Technician II — Michael Baker International              | Jan. 2015 — July 2018 |
| National Flood Insurance Program Contract (FEMA), Alexandria, VA |                       |
| University Research Aide — George Washington University          | Mar. 2014 — Aug. 2014 |
| Geology Department (Advisor: Dr. Richard Tollo), Washington, DC  |                       |
| Student Trainee — U.S. Geological Survey                         | June 2013 — Aug. 2013 |
| Appalachian Blue Ridge Project, Reston, VA                       |                       |

### **Publications**

- Hancock, C. L., Erb, M. P., McKay, N. P., Dee, S. G. (in review). DAMP-21ka: A Data Assimilation of Moisture Patterns for the past 21,000 years. *Climate of the Past*, EGUsphere [preprint]. https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2024-746
- McKay, N. P., Kaufman, D. K., Arcusa, S., Kolus, H., Edge, D., Erb, M. P., <u>Hancock, C. L.</u>, Routson, C. R., Zarczyński, M., Marshall, L. P., Roberts, G., Telles, F. (in review). The 4.2 ka event is not remarkable in the context of Holocene climate variability. *Nature Communications*
- Hancock, C. L., McKay, N. P., Erb, M. P., Kaufman, D. S., Routson, C. R., Ivanovic, R. F., Gregoire, L. J., and Valdes, P. (2023). Global synthesis of regional Holocene hydroclimate variability using proxy and model data. Paleoceanography and Paleoclimatology, 38, e2022PA004597. https://doi.org/10.1029/2022PA004597

Erb, M. P., McKay, N. P., Steiger, N., Dee, S., <u>Hancock, C.</u>, Ivanovic, R. F., Gregoire, L. J., and Valdes, P. (2022). Reconstructing Holocene temperatures in time and space using paleoclimate data assimilation. *Climate of the Past*, 18, 2599–2629. https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-18-2599-2022, 2022

### Conference & Workshop Presentations (First Author Only)

- 2023 Hancock, C., Erb, M.P., McKay, N., "DAMP-21ka: Data Assimilation of Moisture Patterns (21 ka present) using lake-level proxy records" American Geophysical Union (AGU) fall meeting, San Francisco CA. (poster)
  - Hancock, C., "Analyzing & compositing proxy data" Data Assimilation Workshop, Flagstaff, AZ. (oral)
  - Hancock, C., "Present upcoming Holocene hydroclimate proxy database & reconstruction", PAGES 2k Phase 4 Workshop, Potsdam, Germany. (invited seminar)
- 2022 Hancock, C., McKay, N., Erb, M.P., Gregoire, L.J., Ivanovic, R.F., Valdes, P.J., "Global synthesis of regional Holocene hydroclimate variability using proxy and model data" American Geophysical Union (AGU) fall meeting, Chicago IL. (oral)
  - Hancock, C., "Analyzing & compositing proxy data" Data Assimilation Workshop, Flagstaff, AZ. (oral)
- 2021 Hancock, C., McKay, N., Erb, M.P., Gregoire, L.J., Ivanovic, R.F., Valdes, P.J., "Holocene Hydroclimate: Multi Millennial-Scale Trends in Proxies and Models" American Geophysical Union (AGU) fall meeting, New Orleans LA. (poster)
  - Hancock, C. "Hydroclimate of the San Juan Mountains, Colorado" Association of American Geographers (AAG) annual meeting, Seattle WA. (oral)
- 2019 Hancock, C. "Hydroclimate of the San Juan Mountains, Colorado" Association of American Geographers (AAG) annual meeting, Washington DC. (poster)

### Teaching Experience (Instructor of Record)

#### Northern Arizona University

Climate Change ENV 115 Summer 2022

### Teaching Experience (Teaching Assistant)

#### Northern Arizona University

| Geological Disasters Lab                 | GLG 112L    | Spring 2022                          |
|--|-------------|--------------------------------------|
| Senior Seminar in Environmental Sciences | ENV 490C    | Spring 2022                          |
| Geomorphology Lab                        | ENV 259L    | Fall 2021                            |
| Environmental Sustainability             | ENV 181     | Fall 2021                            |
| University of Denver                     |             |                                      |
| Environmental Systems Lab                | GEOG 1201-3 | Fall 2019; Winter/Spring/Summer 2020 |
| George Washington University             |             |                                      |
| Historical Geology Lab                   | GLG 1002    | Spring 2014                          |
| Environmental Geology Lab                | GLG 1005    | Fall 2013                            |

Chris Hancock CV Page 2

## Service

| Departmental Committees: | PhD Student Representative — Northern Arizona University | 2023 — 2024 |
|--------------------------|--|-------------|
|                          | D&I Committee Member — Northern Arizona University       | 2022 — 2024 |
|                          | Graduate Student Representative — University of Denver   | 2019 — 2020 |

Journal Reviewer: Earth System Science Data, Nature Communications

## Outreach

| ARCS Awards Dinner (Phoenix, AZ) — Achievement Rewards for College Scientists Foundation                                  | 4/21/2023  |
|---|------------|
| Be in the Know: Water and Future Development in Arizona Event (Payson, AZ) — Arizona Association for Economic Development | 11/16/2022 |

# Funding, Grants, & Awards

| 2023 - ARCS Scholar Award                                | \$8,500 |
|--|---------|
| - Tom and Rose Bedwell Earth Physics Research Award      | \$1,550 |
| 2022 - Tom and Rose Bedwell Earth Physics Research Award | \$1,000 |
| - Rod Parnell Fund for Water Resources Research Support  | \$500   |
| 2021 - Pioneer Natural Resources Research Award          | \$1,800 |
| - Tom and Rose Bedwell Earth Physics Research Award      | \$1,600 |
| - EarthCube Early Career Travel Grant                    | \$1,500 |
| 2019 - Laurance C. Herold Fund                           | \$850   |

### **Technical Skills**

Python, R, ArcGIS, QGIS, SQL, GitHub, & Adobe Illustrator